<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A spittle sermon preach'd in St. Brides Parish-Church, on Wednesday in Easterweek, being the second day of April, 1684 before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor, the Court of Aldermen, and the sheriffs of the now Protestant, and loyal city of London / by Thomas Pittis ...</title>
            <author>Pittis, Thomas, 1636-1687.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54949</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2318</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10785</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13114272</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13114272</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97733</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54949)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97733)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 749:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A spittle sermon preach'd in St. Brides Parish-Church, on Wednesday in Easterweek, being the second day of April, 1684 before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor, the Court of Aldermen, and the sheriffs of the now Protestant, and loyal city of London / by Thomas Pittis ...</title>
                  <author>Pittis, Thomas, 1636-1687.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B.W. for Edward Vize ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: prelim. p. [5]-[6].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Ecclesiastes II, 6 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97733:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97733:1"/>
            <p>A <hi>Spittle Sermon</hi> PREACH'D In S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> BRIDES Pariſh-Church, on <hi>Wedneſday</hi> in <hi>Eaſter Week,</hi> being the Second Day of <hi>April,</hi> 1684.</p>
            <p>BEFORE The Right Honourable the Lord Mayor, THE Court of ALDERMEN, and the SHERIFFS of the now Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, and Loyal, City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>THOMAS PITTIS,</hi> D. D. Rector of S. <hi>Botolph</hi> without <hi>Biſhopsgate London,</hi> and one of His Majeſties Chaplains in Ordinary.</p>
            <q>Ecce quàm invicem ſe amant!</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>B. W.</hi> for <hi>Edward Vize,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Biſhop</hi>'s <hi>Head</hi> over againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> MDCLXXXIV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:97733:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97733:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Henry Tulſe, LORD MAYOR, and to the Right Worſhipful the Court of AL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DERMEN and SHERIFFS of the City of <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>May it pleaſe your Lordſhip,</hi> &amp;c.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN obedience to your juſt Authority, which I have alwayes, in my ſmall Sphere, endeavoured to maintain, I have hardned my ſelf againſt the Cenſures of the World, to comply with your deſire to Print a mean Diſcourſe on a Noble Theme. God grant that you may, under the Supreme
<pb facs="tcp:97733:3"/>
Being, and a moſt excellent King, perfect <hi>the Thorow Reformation according to Law,</hi> which you have begun; be as Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable, and Kind, as the following Sermon was deſigned, by the Preacher, to exhort you unto; and alwayes Loyal to that <hi>Moſt Proteſtant, and truly Gracious, Monarch,</hi> who gave you your Commiſſion; whilſt I remain,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Right Honourable,</hi> &amp;c.</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt humble, and moſt obedient Servant, <hi>THO. PITTIS.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:97733:3"/>
            <head>Theſe Books following are written by the ſame Author, and are to be ſold by <hi>Edward Vize,</hi> at the <hi>Biſhop</hi>'s <hi>Head</hi> over againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Diſcourſe of Prayer: Wherein this great Duty is ſtated, ſo as to oppoſe ſome Principles and Practices of <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Fanaticks;</hi> as they are contrary to the Publick Forms of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by her Eccleſiaſtical Canons, and confirmed by Acts of Parliament.</p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe concerning the Tryal of Spirits: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Inquiry is made into Mens Pretences to Inſpiration for publiſhing Doctrines in the Name of God, beyond the Rules of the Sacred Scriptures. In oppoſition to ſome Principles and Practices of <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Fanaticks;</hi> as they contradict the Doctrines of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> defined in her Articles of Religion, eſtabliſhed by her Eccleſiaſtical Canons, and confirmed by Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:97733:4"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 3. line 23. read <hi>their abode:</hi> p. 20. l. 21. r. <hi>Antoninus Pius:</hi> p. 24. l. 5. blot out <hi>He:</hi> p. 27. l. 5. inſtead of <hi>Streams,</hi> r. <hi>Steames.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97733:4"/>
            <head>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Eccleſiaſtes 11.6. former part.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>In the morning ſow thy ſeed; and, in the evening, withhold not thine hand.—</p>
               </q>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the fore-going Verſes of this Chapter, we have directions and motives to diſperſe our Alms, the bleſſed fruits of an enlarged Charity: A word ſo big and comprehenſive, (when 'tis not reſtrained as in this Text) that it points out the whole duty of man. This Vertue, being ſo ſacred and divine a Grace, is the foundation of all Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, mentioned both in the Law, and by the Prophets; ſo that our Bleſſed Saviour himſelf informs us, That, as to <hi>love the Lord our God with all our heart, with all our ſoul, and with all our ſtrength,</hi> contains the general matter of the firſt Table of the Law: So, to <hi>love our neighbour as our ſelves,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:97733:5"/>
includes the ſecond, (<hi>Matth.</hi> 22.37, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) To the ſecond of theſe is my Text confined; and though liberal acts are here wrap'd up in Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor; yet the words, I have read, are a plain in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timation of as neceſſary a duty of diſperſing our abundance, or ſuperfluities, of this World amongſt thoſe who ſtand in need of our relief. For, the expreſſion of <hi>Seed</hi> ſignifying mens Alms, and <hi>ſowing it,</hi> the diſperſion of them, cannot appear to be terms very far fetch'd; ſince the Scriptures of the New Teſtament, in relation to the Bounty and Liberality of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, ſay, <hi>He which ſoweth ſparingly, ſhall reap ſparingly; and he which ſoweth bountifully, ſhall reap bountifully,</hi> (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.6.) The Seed of our Charity, amongſt other things, <hi>ſpringing up unto eternal life,</hi> may eaſily repreſent both our duty and reward, and engage us to ſcatter and ſow our Alms, ſince ſo large a Crop ſhall abundantly ſatisfie for our labour and expence. It is not rare in Scripture phraſe, but very frequent, to expreſs its meaning in Alluſions or Metaphors, and theſe, by a continued ſucceſſion, are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times advanced to an Allegory: And the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text, in theſe caſes, will eaſily determine their ſenſe and meaning. Thus we find here, in my Text, the ſame duty of diſperſing our Charity, which, in the firſt Verſe of the ſame Chapter, is
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97733:5"/>
adviſed in the expreſſion of <hi>caſting bread upon the face of the waters,</hi> phraſed, now, by <hi>ſowing our ſeed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore, without any torturing Criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſms, or troubling our ſelves with harder lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage; The Text I have taken to diſcourſe on, includes only a clear direction to beſtow our Charity to thoſe who ſtand in need of our aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance. And becauſe men, who are ſo greedy of this World, that they little take care of the advantages of the next, are apt to decline the performance of that, which they cannot but acknowledge to be juſt and equal, and to raiſe objections againſt the practice of what, in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation, they are willing to own; eſpecially in this duty of Charity and Bounty, that cannot be accompliſhed without expence: Becauſe ſome are ſo addicted to ſcrape together the duſt and rubbiſh of this lower World, that their ſweat and blood ſhall be drop'd into it, to make it to conſolidate and cement together, that it may not be ſcattered, but fixed to the places and ſeats of abode: Nay, ſo greedy are ſome for the ſecuring their wealth, and ſo loth to diminiſh any of their heaps, that they will even venture to dye to ſave charges. The wiſe Preacher therefore, in the Chapter of my Text, confirms this neceſſary duty of Charity, by argument;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97733:6"/>
and at the ſame time anſwers objections: And becauſe the rich, though cloſe, men of the World, are apt to think, that ſcattering their wealth, is the way to diminiſh it, and that giving to the needy, is not the method to encreaſe their ſtore; he aſſures them, <hi>ver.</hi> 1. that if they <hi>caſt their bread upon the waters, they ſhall find it after many dayes.</hi> That is, though they throw it into a running ſtream, that is paſſing by, and never like to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the ſame place again; yet it is not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible by a large circulation, to enter by the caverns of the earth, into the ſame River: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, the fountain-head ſtill ſprings, and the great God, of the Sea which is the Parent of the Rivers, can ſend a greater proportion from above; and, in this caſe, unleſs what may be a greater advantage intervenes, his will ſhall not controll his power. But men may, perhaps, be enclined to adventure ſomething upon the bottom of this hope; only they are afraid to ſend any large portion of their wealth upon thoſe waters, that may carry it too far out of their reach: They would diſperſe a ſmall Summ to a few; but they are loth to have the trouble of too many Penſioners. This the Wiſe-man ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viates too, at <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. <hi>Give a portion,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>to ſeven, and alſo to eight;</hi> to ſome, and to more, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy proportion and ability; which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97733:6"/>
one man cannot ſet for another, unleſs he is acquainted with his eſtate and circumſtances: And he adds an Argument, and Motive, to this; <hi>For thou knoweſt not</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>what evil ſhall be upon the earth.</hi> Thou knoweſt not what miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief thou maiſt prevent, by thy Charity, to another: Nor what evils may betide thy ſelf, when thou maiſt, by the mutability of affairs, ſtand in need of help or aſſiſtance from others. But (farther) becauſe, in an affair of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, men are ſo loth to part with that wealth, which they love ſo well; and to reſign a poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, in hope only of a future reverſion; and therefore are very curious in making their choice of thoſe Objects, on whom they may beſtow their Charity; which muſt coſt them that money which they prize equal to their lives. The Preacher ſends them to take a view of the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Heavens, and fetches an argument out of the Clouds; that they may not alwayes look upon the Earth, but ſometimes lift up their eyes to Heaven. <hi>If the clouds</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>be full of rain, they empty themſelves upon the earth:</hi> And that none may be diſheartned, or rather willingly excuſe themſelves, from Noble, and Godlike acts of Bounty, becauſe the Receivers are frequently ſo unworthy, or ingrateful; the Wiſe-man goes on in the third Verſe, <hi>If the tree
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97733:7"/>
fall towards the ſouth, or towards the north,</hi> it is indifferent, ſo it falls at all; for <hi>in the place where the tree falleth, there it ſhall be.</hi> Thy Charity, however, let the receiver be never ſo unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy or unthankful, ſhall be accepted by him, who has enjoyned it as thy duty, if thou haſt placed it with a good mind. For he, that uſually ſtayes too long wavering and delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting about ſuch things as theſe, miſſes often a fitting Object, and frequently does not give at all; but loſes his ſeaſon and reward too: he ſlips his ſeed time, and cannot well expect an har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt. For (as it follows, <hi>ver.</hi> 4.) <hi>He that obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the wind, will not ſow; and he that regardeth the clouds, ſhall not reap.</hi> So that, upon the whole, when we are able, we muſt be alwayes wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to give; Becauſe (as it is in the latter part of the Verſe, in which my Text is placed) with reference either to time or perſons, we may eaſily be deceived; For <hi>we know not what gift may proſper;</hi> either this, or that; or whether they may not be alike good. Give often therefore, as <hi>Seneca</hi> adviſeth, becauſe <hi>perdenda ſunt multa, ut ſemel ponas bene;</hi> many are to be loſt, that you may ſometimes, or, at leaſt once, place your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits well. However, follow the advice in my Text, <hi>In the morning ſow thy ſeed, and in the evening withhold not thine hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:97733:7"/>And now, theſe words, from their plain co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence with the former part of this Chapter, preſent to us that publick duty of Charity to thoſe who ſtand in need of our aid and relief. A duty that is inſcribed on the minds of men, which nature it ſelf inclines us to; So that we muſt renounce the Principles of Humanity, and bid defiance to the diſpoſitions of our minds (if they are not fill'd with dirt and rubbiſh, or ſhrunk by an unnatural, nay, deviliſh fierceneſs and cruelty) when we refuſe to commiſerate perſons in affliction, or ceaſe to be, according to our abilities, charitable to the Poor. The <hi>Jews</hi> would formerly have directed us to this duty; The <hi>Heathen</hi> will upbraid us, if we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce it; The <hi>Beaſts</hi> themſelves will gladly ſuffer their own kind to feed with them; And the <hi>damned in Hell</hi> have had ſo much kindneſs and compaſſion too, to wiſh well to their Brethren, even whilſt themſelves have been tormented in the flames: Charity is a duty pleaſant in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, glorious in it ſelf, and brings a large, and a rich portion, to thoſe who love, and therefore eſpouſe, it: For it entitles men to the bleſſing of God, which, the Scripture tells us, <hi>maketh rich:</hi> 'Tis that which the covetous, and ſordid men of this lower World will commend in others, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they may be loth to practiſe it themſelves:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97733:8"/>
Nay, the Devils in Hell will laugh at us, when we ceaſe to be kind to our own ſpecies: 'Tis that, without which, all our larger proprieties muſt ceaſe; Humane Government and Society muſt be diſſolved: and if a tolerable care were not taken of the Needy, the greateſt Empires would quickly be laid in duſt and ruines, when the Poor are every where more numerous, and conſequently, ſtronger, than the rich: It pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves Power and Authority among us, whilſt Order, betwixt ſuperiors and inferiors, is, by a ſuitable allowance to the different ſtates and ranks of men, not violated, but preſerved en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire. The rich cannot live, without the poor; and in common prudence, they ought to be maintained, that ſome may do the drudgery of the World: We may as well think, that Trade and Commerce can be ſupported with Foreign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers without Ships, to tranſport the growth and product of our own ſoil, and bring to us the advantages of another: That theſe flying Arks, riding on the Waves, and mounted by the wings of the Wind, can ſail with ſafety, and directly, to their Ports, by the ſteeridge of a Pilot, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out common Sea-men, that may, with toil and labour, hoiſt, or ſhift, or take in the Sails. What pitiful Trades ſhould we quickly have in this renowned City, had we not Porters, and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97733:8"/>
to bear the burdens? How would the deſtroying Plague invade us, had we not Scaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to cleanſe the Streets? Nay, Great men, and the moſt delicate Ladies, would hardly know how to live; but Peſtilence, and Infection would ſeiſe their Houſes, and the very Air, in which they breathe, had they not thoſe contented, and in their condition, happy Inferiors, to endure the heat and burthen of the day, whilſt they keep all ſweet and clean. So that the Rich can no more live without the Poor, than they can with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Rich. But, beſides all this, the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, which we profeſs, more eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally enjoyns Charity to its Diſciples; not only that love, which, if ſincere, will, certainly, <hi>cover a multitude of ſins;</hi> but alſo their Alms and Bounty, to relieve others: That whilſt the Rich enjoy their State and Plenty, none may be ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for want of Bread. There is nothing more frequent than Exhortations, and Commands, with reference unto Charity, ſo commonly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed in the New Teſtament, as well as the Old; that to repeat them, would be thought an unreaſonable lengthning of my diſcourſe, and reflect diſparagement upon ſo Religious, and Honourable, an Aſſembly; as if I preached to ſuch, who could not, or did not, read the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:97733:9"/>All therefore that I ſhall at this time farther attempt, ſhall be diſcharged in a performance of two things:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> In ſhewing how this Charity, in diſperſing our Wealth, may, beſides our ordinary and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Alms, be ſo managed, that we may accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh the duty we are directed to in my Text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> In perſwading to the full and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent exerciſe of it; That <hi>in the morning</hi> we may, according to our abilities, <hi>ſow our ſeed, and in the evening may not withhold our hands.</hi> And theſe two things I ſhall endeavour to accompliſh, as plainly, and as briefly, as I may.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Let me exhibit the methods and ways, by which we may expend and lay out our Wealth, that may eaſily be ſpared from our ſelves and families; ſo as to follow the ſacred direction in this Text, and ſeveral other in Holy Writ. And, here, I need not ſpeak of the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Objects that are rendred capable of our Charity and Relief: The Government it ſelf is too often forced to beg, though it is to keep us all in order; And yet it is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs'd without a Free-will-offering, when we are obliged to it, by way of gratitude, for that Peace and Security, under the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of which we enjoy our own. None can think they ſhall want Objects, either deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97733:9"/>
or craving their Charity, though they had a Million to expend in its ſervice, ſuppoſing it to be confined to the limits of this City; if I may meaſure the whole, by the bounds of that part, in which I have my lot and reſidence; though in the computation, we ſhould make a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and vaſt, abatement. Any way that by our Charity we may contribute to the advantage, and welfare, of the Goods, Bodies, or Souls of others, that may want help, and acceſſions, to either, ſo as it be done according to proportion, and opportunity, will, in the general, diſcharge this duty in my Text.</p>
            <p>But, more particularly, there are three cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels, into which our Charity, diſperſing it ſelf, may overflow, to the disburthening the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, by the diſpoſal of our large, or increaſing, <hi>Mammon.</hi> And theſe are Hoſpitality, Liberality, and Munificence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> We may ſow the ſeed of our Wealth (that I may ſometimes uſe the Metaphor in my Text) by being hoſpitable in our houſes, and entertainments: And this does not only ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the dignity of men, to ſet a luſtre on the different Orders in the World, by ſhewing a decent mixture of Authority and Wealth, that uphold each other. But it invites Inferiors, and thoſe that are entertained, not only to an awful,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97733:10"/>
and affectionate, regard to the hoſpitable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; But it cauſes men to be acquainted with, and to love, each other by keeping up a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and, as far as it is fitting, a familiar, friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; that ſo Order may be the Parent of Peace; and there may be no Jars or Diſcords in our va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Societies, nor any Complaints heard in our Streets. This vertue of Hoſpitality, the <hi>Greeks</hi> were wont to expreſs by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as if it were an eſſential ingredient to the hoſpitable man to make his entertainments, not to flow from neceſſity, but delight: And therefore the pleaſure that accrued to him from his kindneſs to ſtrangers, might be a great compenſation for the charge and expence. But farther yet, The exerciſe of this Splendid and Noble Vertue, gains not only Honour and Reputation in the World, but Friends too. And it is not unfre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently rewarded in this life, by ſuch correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencies and acceſſions to our Wealth, by a kind reception of grateful gueſts, that more than dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble our favours upon our ſelves. However, if an affable, courteous and generous temper ſhould not attract to its Owner, its due and juſt reward here, through any ill Fate, or the Ingratitude of others; but be upbraided by diſingenuity and unkindneſs; yet, to be ſure, he ſhall not alwayes miſs his recompence: For his large mind ſhall,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97733:10"/>
in a future Region, enter where an Eſtate can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not; and gain a glorious and eternal habitation, when his moſt ſtately Manſion in this World; nay, the Palaces of Princes ſhall prove ſo rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, that they can no longer houſe their Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants. For the great God has ſo twiſted our intereſt with our duty, that he who commands us to uſe Hoſpitality, inſtamping this ſacred Vertue upon our minds, writing it alſo in large characters in the Old Teſtament and the New, has graciouſly promiſed to reward theſe actions; though their native goodneſs is a ſufficient ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to recommend their practice. If we receive, therefore, ſtrangers with compaſſion and courteſie, or ſupply the wants of thoſe, whoſe neceſſitous inability, or preſent misfortunes, cannot make proviſion for themſelves; The moſt gracious God, whoſe nature is to be libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, will not only conduct us in our Pilgrimage here, but hereafter allot us eternal Manſions, full of quiet and pleaſant repoſe, when our dayes ſhall be accompliſhed in this lower World, and the diſſolution of our bodies ſhall put a period to the enjoyment of thoſe poſſeſſions which we have yet the fruition of. It was always, amongſt mankind, not only a piece of good Nature, but Religion, to provide for, and protect, to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of their power, him whom their Favour
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97733:11"/>
and Hoſpitality, admitted as a gueſt into their houſes: Hence was it, that the old man of <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heah,</hi> when he had received the travelling <hi>Levite</hi> into his houſe, at ſuch a time as the whole Town were inhoſpitable, and the Hectoring Blades of the Sons of <hi>Belial,</hi> had a reſolution to break the Sacred Bonds, not only of Hoſpitality, but Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity too; and to that end, beſet the houſe, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out with a large and common throat, <hi>Bring forth the man that came into thine houſe, that we may know him:</hi> offering not only violence to their neighbour, and to one, whoſe Function, being Sacred, might have been his protection, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when he was a ſtranger too; but to the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral propenſity, and Laws of mankind: yet the good old man quickly reprehended ſuch rude violence, though with Rhetorick that might have ſoftned the moſt uncultivated Clowns, or any except ſuch Miſcreants as theſe: <hi>Nay, my brethren,</hi> (ſayes he, <hi>ver.</hi> 23.) <hi>nay, I pray you do not ſo wickedly:</hi> And he draws his Argument from the common right and Laws of hoſpitality; <hi>See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this man is come into mine houſe, do not this folly.</hi> Now this is not the only reaſon to preſerve the rights of hoſpitality ſacred; But the great God (whom all mankind have cauſe to fear) was not only angry at their rudeneſs and incivility; but utterly diſſatisfied with, and reſolved to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97733:11"/>
puniſh the crimes both of their deſire and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And this appears in the ſucceeding puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: For though the merits of the cauſe are exhibited to us (<hi>Judges</hi> 19.) yet it is apparent, in the next Chapter, that although the body of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> loſt forty thouſand in two Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels; the <hi>Benjamites</hi> had their Cities reduced to aſhes, and their Beaſts and Men ſmitten with the Sword, and only ſix hundred eſcaped this pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, like <hi>Job</hi>'s meſſengers, that the diſlike of ſuch crimes might be continued to poſterity. Nor is this example only upon record to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage hoſpitality, and deterr men from acting contrary to the Laws of it; But there are alſo more early patterns of this Vertue, and great advantages that did attend it. <hi>Abraham</hi> exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing hoſpitality to ſtrangers, had the honour to entertain three Angels; and not only ſo, but at the ſame time, he had the aſſurance of a moſt gracious Promiſe, that a Son ſhould yet ſpring from the barren Womb, <hi>in whom all the Nations of the earth ſhould be bleſſed, (Gen.</hi> 18.). His Kinſman <hi>Lot</hi> alſo, becauſe Generoſity then, as it does often now, ran in a blood, was honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with two Angels for his gueſts, in the very next Chapter: And though the wickedneſs of the <hi>Sodomites</hi> ſeemed to blemiſh and ſpoil the Feaſt, in cauſing this Entertainment to be Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97733:12"/>
to themſelves; yet hoſpitable <hi>Lot</hi> was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried from the devouring flames, and plucked as a Brand, out of this dreadful fire, that reduced the whole City into aſhes: Now leſt any nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and griping <hi>Preciſian</hi> ſhould baniſh the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent uſe of hoſpitality, becauſe the genero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of ſome may be abuſed to the debauchery of others, (as ſome perſons have an excellent Talent to inveigh againſt the abuſes, nay, the very uſe of things, which, if allowed, muſt ſometimes prove chargeable to themſelves): Leſt ſuch, I ſay, ſhould too much ſtraiten the Vertue of hoſpitality, as a thing too looſe for a Goſpel Diſpenſation, and not agreeable to Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual diſpoſitions, that muſt be fed with a thinner diet; Thoſe two examples, juſt now fetched out of the Old Teſtament, are placed in the New, to encourage that hoſpitality which its Precepts do enjoyn: <hi>Be not forgetful to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſtrangers,</hi> (ſayes the Author to the <hi>Hebrews) for thereby ſome have entertained Angels unawares.</hi> Nor is this a duty commanded only to the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy under the New Teſtament, from whom men are frequently ſo unjuſt, as to expect much, where leſs is given; But all other perſons as well as theſe are commanded to be <hi>given to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitality,</hi> even all the houſhold and family of the faithful: And therefore S. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts all
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97733:12"/>
(<hi>Rom.</hi> 12.13.) to <hi>diſtribute to the neceſſities of the Saints,</hi> and to be <hi>given to hoſpitality.</hi> And S. <hi>Peter</hi> alſo backs him in this, by adviſing men to <hi>uſe hoſpitality one to another, without grudging;</hi> And <hi>as every man hath received the gift,</hi> (his proportion of outward and worldly bleſſings) <hi>ſo miniſter the ſame one to another, as good ſtewards of the manifold grace of God,</hi> (1 Pet. 4.9, 10.). Nay, there are not only Precepts to command, and Motives to encourage to this duty in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but Examples too, could I ſpare ſo much time on this Head, to produce them. What ſhould I tell you of devout <hi>Lydia</hi>'s en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> and thoſe that accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panyed him? (<hi>Acts</hi> 16.15.) of that ſplendid Marriage Feaſt in <hi>Cana</hi> of <hi>Galilee,</hi> at which the Mother of our Lord, our Saviour himſelf, and his Diſciples, were ſo plentifully, nay, abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly treated: (<hi>John</hi> 2.) Of that Parabolical Supper, in the Goſpel, where the Poor, and the maimed, the halt, and the blind were entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; (<hi>Luke</hi> 14.) Nor can I ſtay now to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large upon the hoſpitality of <hi>Publius</hi> exerciſed to S. <hi>Paul</hi> and his Ships Crue, on the Iſland of <hi>Melita</hi> in the <hi>Lybian</hi> Sea, when they had ſuffered a dangerous Shipwrack in a Storm; nor on the common <hi>Barbarians</hi> kindneſs and entertainment, (<hi>Acts</hi> 28.). Let the Old <hi>Germans</hi> ſhame our
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97733:13"/>
little, narrow, ſyſtematical men, and all inho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitable tempers in the World: Of whom, <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus</hi> gives this commendation; That <hi>convictibus &amp; hoſpitiis non alia gens effuſius indulget;</hi> No Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was more free and generous in their enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments: <hi>Quemcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> mortalium arcere tecto nefas habetur; pro fortunâ quiſque apparatis epulis exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit.</hi> They were almoſt prodigal in their hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality: 'Twas a crime, a wickedneſs beyond pardon, to bid any one to depart out of their houſes; and every one entertained ſuitable to his Fortune: Strangers were welcome, as well as Friends, to the Tables and Beds of the hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table man. Amongſt the <hi>Lucani,</hi> who dwelt in <hi>Italy,</hi> it was a ſtanding Law, that if a Stranger came about Sunſet to any ones houſe, to deſire ſhelter, and the Maſter would not permit him to be received, he was preſently to be fined and puniſhed, as a cruel and inhoſpitable man; <hi>Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctetur</hi> (ſayes my Author) <hi>&amp; poenas luat inhoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitatis.</hi> How ſplendid and glorious were ſuch Laws, and a decent and well guarded deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſuitable to them, in compariſon to ſome girdled, and ſtrait waſted, people among our ſelves; when, with them, a man may ſooner break his Neck, than his Faſt; who ſhake their heads at the name of any old obſervation, and yet at home keep an everlaſting <hi>Lent?</hi> But alas!
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97733:13"/>
ſuch men, what ever mortification they pretend, are ſo far off from the principles of Religion, that they are not arrived at good manners, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending Temperance, and Abſtinence, and the frequent abuſes of open hoſpitality, to hide their Avarice, under the Mantle of Vertue, and a more ſtrict Sobriety: And yet all this while there are none more frequent gueſts to other men, than ſuch as are averſe to tolerable en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainments at their own houſes: But when they are guilty of a forced rape upon their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon inclinations, and honour cauſes covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to bleed, they give the entertained a Meal, only that they may run the Spit into their Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies; and like one ſort of cruel Heathens, ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice their gueſts to their <hi>Diana:</hi> Alas! how many Treats are made in the World, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſole deſign of preying on the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained, filling their Bellies, that they may empty their Purſes; and laying them to ſleep, that they may pick their Pockets, or elſe rob them of their principles of Honeſty or Religion: Nay, too often, men, under the guiſe of hoſpitality, defraud others of their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and reputation, ſacrificing the good name of a preſent gueſt, to thoſe gods of the World, that may ſucceed them in the next entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to whom, greater intereſt commands
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97733:14"/>
greater oblations, whilſt they ſport together with blemiſhing the Fame of an abſent Acquaintance: Though by ſuch treachery, among good men, we ſpoil our entertainments, and with the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of our Gueſts, we conſume our Honour and our Honeſty too. Yet the fault muſt not alwayes lye at the door of him who is given to hoſpitality, but ſometimes the gueſt may ſpoil the entertainment, not only by a tatling humour, and a cenſorious branding; nay, rip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping up the bowels, and unveiling the faults of ſuch acquaintance, as are common to both; But he may offer injury to the hoſpitable man, and diſcourage him in the exerciſe of this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous duty, which cements men together by love and friendſhip, and relieves thoſe that are in want and miſery: And this is done by unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable approaches, or being over-curious in queſtions and enquiries, or garrulous and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in other places, of what paſſed at the laſt entertainment. <hi>Antonius Pius</hi> asking one, Where he had thoſe Porphyry Pillars? he preſently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, with ſome ſmartneſs, <hi>In alienis aedibus &amp; mutum, &amp; ſurdum, eſſe decet; Under anothers roof, it is decent to be both deaf and dumb.</hi> But not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this, the accidental abuſes of a generous hoſpitality, muſt not diſcourage the practice of ſo laudable a Vertue; but we muſt,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97733:14"/>
according to our ſtations and abilities, cheerfully receive, civilly entertain, and courteouſly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs thoſe, whom a ſolemn invitation, a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon accident, or an urging neceſſity, makes our gueſts; according to that of the Antient Poet,
<q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And now I might, juſtly, take occaſion to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigh againſt thoſe Great and Rich men in the World, that have ſhrivel'd Hearts and ſwoln Purſes, who are ſo far from being hoſpitable to others, that they are narrow and unjuſt to their Families and themſelves. But as I am not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to offend the <hi>Gentile,</hi> ſo I am loth to upbraid the very <hi>Jew.</hi> And therefore I come to my ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Head; under which, we may ſow the ſeed of Charity, in a bounteous liberality to thoſe whom Providence cauſes to live upon that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, which the Almighty Lord of the whole World, demands as a Quit-rent, from thoſe, to whom he has granted an Eſtate, it being his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar reſerve and portion.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe the earthy gifts of this World, cannot immediately reach Heaven, though we raiſe never ſo much duſt with them (for <hi>our goodneſs extends not to God, Pſal.</hi> 16.2.) The glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97733:15"/>
King of the whole World receives not theſe reſerved Rents himſelf; which our Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour plainly intimates, upon previſion of his Aſcenſion into Heaven (<hi>John</hi> 12.8.) <hi>The poor ye have alwayes with you; but me you have not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes.</hi> Therefore this Vertue of Liberality, commanded by him who is liberal to us all, is practiſed, by being generous and free to thoſe neceſſitous perſons among our ſelves, from whom we may expect no other returns than gratitude, and ingenuity; <hi>Parum tribuere ut accipias, magis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natio appellanda quam donatio,</hi> ſays St. <hi>Jerom; To be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow a ſmall Boon</hi> (or a great one either) <hi>that we may receive again, is rather a Sale than a Gift.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the liberal man flies higher, and will not ſtoop his Charity to ſuch mean deſigns; nor will he let his benevolence to Hire: And as he does not thus bait his Hook, to catch Fiſh with Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney in their mouths; ſo neither does he adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture his bountiful diſperſions, that his returns may be popularity and fame; though this will always be an attendant: Becauſe they are too mean Conſequences of Liberality to be its ultimate ſcope and end: Hence is that Satyrical Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of our Saviour againſt that old Phariſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Oſtentation, where they blew their Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets when they gave their Alms; and deemed their Gifts ill beſtowed if their Charity were not
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97733:15"/>
publiſhed to the World: It ſeems Glory and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown was the great gain which theſe narrow ſoul'd Creatures ſought for, and deſigned this thin and aiery purchace when they gave an Alms; Therefore the great Lord of the whole Harveſt injoins Chriſtians to be rather ſecret in their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals, and that they ſhould be ſo far from boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their Charity, and noiſing it abroad a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other men, that (if 'twere poſſible) they ſhould not mind it themſelves; nor the left hand know what the right hand did. (<hi>Matth.</hi> 6.3.) <hi>Seneca,</hi> alſo, who is an excellent Moraliſt, to ſay no more, (in his 7th. Book <hi>de beneficiis, cap.</hi> 22.) perſwades the Donor to forget his gift, leſt he ſhould be tempted to boaſt and publiſh it: And he farther reflects on thoſe men <hi>Qui be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficium, quod dederunt, omnibus circulis narrant: That proclaim their Charity on the Stage; and in all Societies brag of their Liberality.</hi> That grave Check which <hi>Solomon</hi> gives to vain-glorious Men, may, in this, gag our Mouths to ſilence (<hi>Prov.</hi> 27.2.) <hi>Let another man praiſe thee, and not thine own Lips:</hi> For, to publiſh our own vertue, is to become an Herauld to our ſelves; and vainly to aſſume the Enſignes of Honour without authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty from thoſe in whoſe power is the right to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them: Nay, at the ſame time, when we boaſt our Liberality, we detract from our repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97733:16"/>
and bounty too, and blazoning our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the wrong way we ſhadow and diſgrace them. Our Saviour, therefore, when he had exerciſed that work of Charity and Mercy in curing the Leper, (<hi>Luke</hi> 5.13.) he ſtrictly char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges him to tell no Man. The caſe is the ſame in Alms and Bounty; endeavouring to be po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular by Oſtentation, not only loſes the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the gift, and the reward from Heaven; but the publick fame which is this way ſought, we defeat our ſelves of by the manner of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance. For he who publiſhes his own Charity, does not only render himſelf ridiculous, but of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes upbraids the Receiver, turning his kindneſs into an enſnaring Cruelty, and makes Enemies inſtead of Friends: Nay, thoſe gifts are juſtly to be ſuſpected as deſigns and traps, that come from ſuch upbraiding Adverſaries. Hence has it been a trite Obſervation, by its age and uſe turned into a Proverb, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The Preſents of Enemies, are none at all;</hi> which wiſe <hi>Solomon</hi> plainly confirms (<hi>Pro.</hi> 27.6.); <hi>Faithful are the wounds of a Friend, but the kiſſes of an Enemy are deceitful.</hi> It is no ſmall acceſſion to the Bounty of Heaven, that all its gifts are free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſtowed; without an expectation of other returns than due gratitude from the Receivers; And though the Supream Being beſtows liberal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97733:16"/>
he never upbraids thoſe on whom he confers his Bleſſings: (<hi>Jam.</hi> 1.5.) So is it with the truly liberal man, who has the Stamp of God upon him; he is ſo generous in his Diſpoſals, the exerciſe of his vertue, that as he contemns thoſe pitiful and mean deſigns to make his gifts become nets to draw worldly advantages to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; So does he as much abhor to betray men by ſuch Hypocritical methods: He mixes no poyſon in that Cup with which he willingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhes a thirſty Traveller, nor is his compaſſion a fair Prologue to any Tragical execution of his Gueſt, nor does he expreſs his kindneſs to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to gain the fairer opportunity to expoſe him: And, indeed, Bounty and Liberality have not their accents of honour given them ſo much from the greatneſs of their gifts, as they are raiſed from the mind and affection of the Donor; One Oblation, therefore, readily ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred upon a low Altar from a willing mind, is better than a conſtrained <hi>Hecatomb: Multò gratius venit quod facili, quam quod plenâ, manu, datur: That gift, though in it ſelf mean, which is eaſily ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, is much more acceptable than that which is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted by much importunity, though the hand be full which at laſt conveys it.</hi> He that beſtows a Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table gift as great and large as the Language that deſcribes it, if it be not without many doubts
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97733:17"/>
and ſhrugs, and ſuch groaning Circumſtances as proclaim inquietude, and unwillingneſs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in him, <hi>Ambitioni dedit, non mihi,</hi> ſays <hi>Seneca: He gave not to me, but to his own Ambition;</hi> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he that gives a little with a willing mind, is more to be regarded than he that is ſcrued to a larger Bounty, and muſt have an engine to untie his Purſe. For as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the riches of the World are the Materials to ſet up the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral man, ſo the charity of the perſon is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together to be meaſured by the dimenſions of the gift, but by the mind and ability of the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtower: <hi>Dabo egenti, ſed ut ipſe non egeam;</hi> (ſays the Moraliſt) <hi>Sic ſuccurram perituro, ſed ut ipſe non peream: I will give to the neceſſitous, ſo as not to bring Poverty to my ſelf; and I will ſo relieve him whoſe miſery forces him to petition for redreſs, that I may not throw my ſelf into the pity and compaſſion of others:</hi> Therefore the Liberal man, whom pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence muſt guard, is not ſo prodigal of his Bounty, but that he will reſerve a Subſiſtence for his Family; nor will he be ſo narrow and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd, but that according to his Proportions he will be the author of good to others. So that as our income ſhould be the meaſure of our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burſments, and our Charity muſt not exceed the proportion of our Receipts; yet we ought not to plead a needleſs poverty when fit Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97733:17"/>
implore our relief. For as a profuſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digality is frequently forced to ſhed tears at its own Funeral; So a griping avarice is often an invitation to Birds of Prey that follow the ſtreams of a loathſom Carkaſs; It executes its Maſter by his own auſterity, and then buries it ſelf with him, and all that it has done for him, was only to help him buy Mourning for himſelf, that he may be accompanied to his Grave with a larger Pomp, and more ſumptuous Solemnity. But he that obſerves the due mean betwixt theſe two oppoſite extreams, and weighs his Bounty by his Poſſeſſions, is not only bleſs'd in his life, lamented at his death, and entails ſmiles and kindneſs on his Poſterity; But he conveys to them, together with his eſtate, the juſt merit of all his Liberality, and the honour and reputation of his ſurviving memory. So that now we may eaſily perceive the rule according to which our Charity is to be extended, by exerciſing Libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity according to proportion: He that has but a ſmaller overplus, may be as bountiful as he that wallows in golden duſt, and glitters with <hi>Indian</hi> ſands about him. <hi>Seneca</hi> that great, and almoſt Evangelical, author, in his firſt Book <hi>de beneficiis,</hi> ch. the eighth, gives us a famous inſtance of this: When many of <hi>Socrates</hi>'s Scholars brought him Preſents in proportion to their Wealth; <hi>Aeſchines</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:97733:18"/>
one of his poor Auditors approach'd him, and told <hi>Socrates</hi> that he could find nothing worthy of him, which he might preſume to give; And, by this ſays he, I know that I am poor. I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent you, therefore, with what is only properly mine, and that's my ſelf; and how ſlender ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the gift may appear, I humbly beg that you would receive it kindly, upon this Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; That others, whilſt they have ſo plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully rewarded your care and pains, have enough left, nay more than they beſtowed. To whom <hi>Socrates</hi> preſently replyed, Haſt thou not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented me with a great gift? Unleſs, perhaps, thou accounteſt thy ſelf little: I will take all the care I can to return thee better than I received thee: Which the Moraliſt applies to confirm the Argument he is treating of, <hi>viz.</hi> That the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Liberality is the largeneſs of the mind rather than the greatneſs of a gift: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he concludes with this Inference; <hi>Vicit Aeſchines, hoc munere, Alcibiadis parem divitiis ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum, &amp; omnium juvenum opulentorum munificentiam. Aeſchines,</hi> by this noble Donation of himſelf, when he had nothing elſe to give his Inſtructor, overcame the greatneſs of <hi>Alcibiades</hi>'s mind, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it was proportionable to his Riches, and out-ſhined the moſt glorious munificence in that rich Auditory. But ſince, an example more
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97733:18"/>
authentick to us, becauſe more ſacred, is ready at hand, that may, at once, extend the practice of this virtue to thoſe of the meaner and more inferiour ſize, and argue our Charity to be then moſt acceptable unto God when it bears an equal proportion to our Riches; I ſhall preſent it to you, that it may be apparent that the Goſpel does not cut Morality ſhorter, but extends it to its juſt length and meaſure. When our Saviour ſaw the rich men caſting their voluntary Oblations into the Treaſury of the Temple; he perceived a poor creeping Widow caſting in two Mites: Upon which he ſaid, (to record it to poſterity) <hi>Of a truth, this poor Widow hath caſt in more than they all: For all theſe have, out of their abundance, caſt in unto the Offerings of God; But ſhe, out of her Penu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, hath caſt in all the living that ſhe has. (Luke</hi> 21.1, 2. <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> So that to be liberal in ſowing our ſeed of Charity, is to be frank upon all juſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions offered, in a true diſtribution according to the proportion of our Wealth, and the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances attending our Eſtates and Families. And now every one beſt knows his Mind, and his Eſtate, and the Freedom or narrowneſs of our own Charity, together with our deliberate apprehenſions of the neceſſities or merits of thoſe that would receive; We have heard Injunctions and Examples from the Law, together with
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97733:19"/>
Precepts, and practice under the Goſpel; and I muſt leave to the Religion and Prudence of all to meaſure the proportion and allotments of their gifts, ſuitable to their Wealth, together with the Objects and deſigns of their Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality,</p>
            <p>And proceed to the laſt general way in which men may ſow the ſeed of their Charity, morning or evening, at every ſeaſonable and fitting op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, accordingly as Objects preſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: And this is called Munificence, or Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence, and by the <hi>Greeks</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. This advances Bounty and Liberality higher in its charge, and ſcatters with a full and larger hand; Yet the Reward hereafter will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely exceed the greateſt weight of our Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences, even in this. Now this concerns the great and mighty men of the World, which a little Wealth cannot accompliſh, and therefore it is an height of Charity, that God and Man can only expect from thoſe to whom the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens have ſhowred down larger allowances, and the Earth and Sea have clubb'd together to make rich. The hoſpitable and the liberal perſon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve only ſudden neceſſities, and grant ſupplies for preſent wants; But the Munificent man lays Foundations and erects Buildings for future ages, and charitably entails an Eſtate on ſuch as are
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:97733:19"/>
Heirs to very little, or none themſelves: And by ſuch great actions, ſplendid and renowned, they erect large Monuments to themſelves, raiſe Pillars to their Immortal fame, on which are engravened the great Characters of Charity and Munificence, not only for the preſent age to read, but for Poſterity to gaze, and comment on: From hence proceeded our publick Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, together with their endowments, that are not confined to ſingle Objects, where the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of the gift does not die with the firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver, but endures as long as Succeſſion laſts, and is continued to many future ages, ſince it is not written in Duſt but Marble, the very ruines of which, if by any iniquity or unfortunate miſhap they are demoliſhed, will remain in the Memories of ſome men as long as the Annals of time ſhall laſt till they become as old as Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory: Hence came our Magnificent Buildings, our Churches, Colledges, Hoſpitals, and the like things that are the glory of a Land; which Domeſticks enjoy, and Foreigners ſtand amazed at, whilſt they make narrow Inſpections into them, and carry reports into their own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, that the Examples may be entered amongſt the Records of time. From hence proceed our publick Revenues that enrich thoſe Buildings which are an Ornament to themſelves; ſo that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97733:20"/>
they become open Atteſtations to the great, tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent, and infinite glory of the Supream God whom we pretend to worſhip; are Seminaries, and publick Schools of Literature, or a laſting, and perpetual, relief to the Poor; They pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim the Religion, and Charity of Nations, and are acceptable to all that ſee, or know, them. Theſe Munificent gifts have been ſo common in former days, that they, almoſt, ſeem need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs in our own. So that Charity, which then ran in one ſtream, has been forced, by Laws, to divert into divers; and yet Chanels are open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for more. So that, although, in ſome times, the ſence of Mens Conſciences may be more affected with theſe things; and they, who receive more than ordinary influence from the Heavens, are ſo ſpurr'd forward to Gratitude and returns, that their inward ſhame may forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly provoke them to publick acts of Benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and Bounty: Yet the reaſon, when time draws men towards the dregs and bottom of the World, why they grow more contracted and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nurious, is not becauſe we have fewer Objects, or leſs Arguments to prevail for our Munificence, but becauſe mens Hearts and Conſciences are narrowed, being heated and ſcorched ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, they are ſhrunk to this, and, by a long and continued time of tenderneſs, they now
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97733:20"/>
grow hard and brawny: Or elſe becauſe their Iniquities abound ſo that the Charity of many is waxen cold, and faſhionable Vices become ſo numerous, that they are alſo very chargeable to maintain. For though it cannot but be appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to the World that, in this great and renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed City, many famous and publick Buildings have, like the <hi>Phoenix,</hi> ariſen out of aſhes, and the Charity of well-diſpoſed perſons has been ſent abroad to both Univerſities, and to other Publick Places of the Land: Yet the increaſe of Wealth muſt alwayes be an argument to enlarge our Bounty, ſince the Neceſſitous will continue to be more numerous, than the Rich: And ſhould we take a view of the large and ſtately Structure of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Temple under the Law, and thereby meaſure the enlarged hearts of the Profeſſors of that antiquated Religion by thoſe many great and ſplendid gifts that were amaſs'd together to compleat the building, and the rich Utenſils that were contained in it; we muſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently vilifie and explode our ſelves, in the ſame Periods in which we magnifie and extol them: There are two Churches that yet lie waſte in this City, which Chriſtian men of ingenuity and Purſe, methinks, ſhould have ſome regard to; (And this I ſpeak with the more confidence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I have no Free-hold in either); the one bears the name of Chriſt, the great Saviour and Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:97733:21"/>
of the World (to which two of your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitals are ſpecially related: The other that of the moſt famous S. <hi>Paul,</hi> who, being his extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Apoſtle, became the Teacher and Doctor of the Gentiles; the poſterity of whom we cannot deny our ſelves to be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> unleſs we had rather be accounted <hi>Jews.</hi> The building theſe, which are now the blemiſh, would mightily ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the ornament, of this City; and far exceed the glory of all the <hi>largeſt Inſcriptions,</hi> and <hi>heighth</hi> of a Monument. But alas! I am too mean to direct: However, I wiſh I had time e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to epitomize Examples of the great Bounty of the Primitive, and moſt refined, Chriſtians, in works of Piety and enlarged Charity; although they were haraſſed with Tryals and Afflictions, yet they liberally diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, what the rage of their adverſaries permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them to enjoy: The Rich and the Poor (the hard ſeaſon then requiring it) threw all into a common bag, laying it at the Apoſtles feet; and rather became Objects of their own Charity, than others ſhould want ſuſtenance and relief: And, afterwards, when the Sun ſhined more favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly on them, they ſcattered their Bounty, as he did his Rayes; <hi>In the morning they ſowed their ſeed, and in the evening they withheld not their hands;</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that in proportion to their ſeed, ſo would the increaſe of their harveſt be. But alas! this would
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:97733:21"/>
be too large a task for me to accompliſh, and too much for you to hear at once: Nay, a Breviary of their pious and charitable works, might ſeem only to enlarge our arraignment, and upbraid our neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects. Let us a little conſider the freſh charity of later Ages, eſpecially that which I am bound to recommend, and that ſhall be all that I will trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you with upon this laſt Head: And here you muſt underſtand the charitable, and encreaſing Fund, by the largeneſs of the Disburſement, which will appear by this <hi>True Report,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>All that I need to note from hence is, what is remark'd in the <hi>Report</hi> it ſelf, that the diſproportion betwixt the Revenue and the Disburſements, is an argument to engage the direction of mens Charity to theſe moſt Chriſtian and Compaſſionate Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations. And now I have nothing elſe remaining, but to exhort you (according to your abilities) to be followers of the beſt and moſt charitable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples: And, in this, I muſt crave leave to beg a rais'd attention, (though it has been already ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently tired) becauſe time commands me to crowd my materials into a narrow room; and only to mention thoſe Heads that might be enlarged to fill a Volume. Charity is ſo great, and ſuch a ſpreading duty, that it makes men to be like God himſelf, who <hi>cauſes his Sun to ſhine,</hi> and ſtrains his refreſhing ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers through the Clouds, <hi>both upon the juſt and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt;</hi> who <hi>giveth liberally,</hi> and <hi>upbraids not the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver.</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:97733:22"/>
It imitates the great Saviour of the World, whoſe Charity to men, was that which brought him down from Heaven, and was the motive that cauſed him to mediate betwixt God and man, that a whole Species might not be eternally ruined. This cauſed him to preach his Doctrine on the earth, to <hi>go about doing good,</hi> and to endure his Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical Tortures and Death. It treads in the ſteps of the holy Spirit of God, who diffuſes the rayes of glorious light, and ſheds his influence on all that are qualified to receive it. Charity is an eternal Vertue, venerable, not only for its excellence, but its age: For as God was from all eternity good, ſo will he remain beyond all periods: And, as this is a Vertue communicated to men, in which he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth, they ſhall carry it with them into the moſt lofty Regions, when they ſhall be for ever with the Lord; when Faith ſhall be ſwallowed up in Viſion and Proſpect, and Hope in an everlaſting Fruition. 'Tis the only way that we have here, by which, <hi>in kind,</hi> we are able to make returns to Almighty God for thoſe outward advantages we receive from him: For our works of Charity, tho' done in obedience to his Commands, cannot im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately reach him; no more than bodily and corruptible things can directly affect, and increaſe, the welfare of that which is immaterial and incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible: And therefore <hi>our goodneſs</hi> (ſayes the <hi>Pſalmiſt) extendeth not to him; but to the Saints which
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:97733:22"/>
are on the earth.</hi> And as we have it in the Book of <hi>Job; Can a man be profitable to God, as he that is wiſe, may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to himſelf?</hi> No certainly: Therefore Charity, that redounds to the relief of others, does, in the end, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn upon our ſelves: And therefore it is a means to encreaſe our Eſtates, and by this the only Objection againſt it muſt vaniſh: For, ſayes the Author of my Text, <hi>Caſt thy bread upon the waters, and thou ſhalt find it after many dayes.</hi> Hence is it, that men are enjoyned, in the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> that they ſhould give to the Poor, without any internal regret, <hi>Becauſe</hi> (ſayes the Text) <hi>for this thing the Lord thy God ſhall bleſs thee in all thy works, and in all that thou putteſt thine hand unto</hi> (Deut. 15.10.). And this promiſe, after full experience, is repeated and atteſted by <hi>Solomon</hi> in his <hi>Proverbs, The liberal ſoul ſhall be made fat; and he that watereth ſhall be watered alſo himſelf. He that giveth to the poor, ſhall not lack; but he that hideth his eyes, ſhall have many a curſe.</hi> And, ſince my hand is in, take that alſo, (Prov. 19.17.) <hi>He that hath pity upon the poor, lendeth unto the Lord, and that which he hath given, will he pay again.</hi> Hence are Alms compared to Seed, in my Text, which, being ſowed, increaſe and multiply. And this, however it may be beyond the view of ſome covetous men, that never were yet generous enough, to adventure the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Yet S. <hi>Paul,</hi> upon the foundation of ſuch Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, encourageth the Charity of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and prayes for their increaſe upon the account of their diſperſion; <hi>Now he that adminiſtreth ſeed to the ſower, both
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:97733:23"/>
miniſter bread for your food, and multiply your ſeed ſown, and increaſe the fruits of your righteouſneſs</hi> (2 Cor. 9.10.). Nay, if we deſire Heaven and the Joyes above, when death ſhall deprive us of our beings here, Charity and Alms are a method to obtain them; For though this way we ſhould diminiſh our treaſures on earth, yet we lay them up in Heaven; and they are only Harbin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, to fore-run our coming: Our Wealth is ſent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand, to furniſh and prepare Manſions for us, and the friends we have made by it whilſt we were upon the earth, have ſent up their Petitions, in the hands of our Mediator, that we may be received into everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing habitations. And therefore, ſayes he, who has the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven, no leſs than thoſe of Death and Hell, <hi>Make to your ſelves friends of the Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of unrighteouſneſs,</hi> (your decaying riches) <hi>that when ye fail, (i. e.)</hi> when ye dye) <hi>they may receive you into ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting habitations</hi> (Luke 16.9.). And what wonder can this be to us? When he that is the Supream Lord of this World, and has the ſole diſpoſal of the next, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts our Charity, as a Sacrifice of his own appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; that which refreſhes, and exceedingly delights, him (<hi>Heb.</hi> 13.16.). It is even as the Incenſe of our Prayers; it ſends a ſweet perfume through the Clouds, till it aſcends before the Throne of God: And, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſayes S. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Cornelius, Thy prayer is heard, and thine Alms are had in remembrance in the ſight of God: (Acts</hi> 10.31.) The truth of which Doctrine he alſo confirms to the <hi>Philippians</hi> (chap. 4.18.) <hi>I have received,</hi> ſays he,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:97733:23"/>
               <hi>the gifts that were ſent from you; a Sacrifice acceptable, well pleaſing to God;</hi> And as his deſire, before, was to receive their Charity, that fruit might abound to their own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; ſo it immediately follows, that God ſhould ſupply all their need according to his riches in glory by Jeſus Chriſt. Indeed the exerciſe of Charity to thoſe that are in want, is an exemplification of that rule of Juſtice, given by our Saviour, to do to others what we would they ſhould do to us, if our circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances and conditions were exchanged; a rule ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded by the reaſon of mankind, that no perſon of ſenſe can oppoſe it: <hi>Alexander Severus</hi> ſo highly va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued it, that he cauſed it to be proclaimed by a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Cryer; to be written on the Walls of his Palace, and publick buildings, (as <hi>Lampridius</hi> tells us in his Life, <hi>cap.</hi> 43.). To conclude, then, this long Diſcourſe in a word; We all profeſs our ſelves to be Chriſtians, and we have plainly heard, that our Religion obliges us to more eſpecial acts of Charity and Bounty; and this not only by peremptory Commands, but we have Examples enough of it; and all is attended with Arguments and Motives fully ſufficient to perſwade to it. And becauſe ours is, for the moſt part, a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering Religion, and 'tis under God, the Goodneſs of our Prince, and the Laws by which he ſtill governs us, and the Religion and Courage of his ſubordinate Magiſtrates, that free us from it at this time: yet no man that is a true Profeſſor of Chriſtianity, is able al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to ſecure himſelf: Nor can any Enſurers in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:97733:24"/>
the World, give us ſecurity, that we ſhall not ſtand in need from others: Charity, therefore, to impove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed perſons, that are modeſt, and in diſtreſs, will be a probable ſecurity to us for the future. Finally, add to all theſe numerous, begging Arguments, That the great God, whom we worſhip through Jeſus Chriſt, has, by the publication of the moſt glorious Goſpel, freed mankind from all thoſe numerous and chargeable Ceremonies, and Sacrifices, pretended to be obligatory, either by <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Gentiles,</hi> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed the Time and the Wealth of thoſe which were devoted to any Religion; by this enabling us Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to be more expenſive in our Charity and Bounty; and this is a return he expects from us for all our plenty that we do enjoy; and this he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and requires of us, according to proportion; that ſo we may have our more ſpiritual Sacrifices ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted by him through the beloved Jeſus Chriſt, the moſt good, compaſſionate, and charitable man that ever was here upon the earth; who being, alſo, God bleſſed for ever; To him, with the Father, and the Holy Ghoſt, let us render, as we ought to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge due, all poſſible Praiſe, Adoration, and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, now and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
